Finding Aid for Thomas R. Wolanin papers, 1989-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas R. Wolanin papers 1989-1997
Wolanin, Thomas R., 1942-
06104 Aa 2
Thomas Wolanin was staff director for the US House Subcommittee on Postsecondary Education within the Education and Labor Committee. He later became assistant secretary for legislation and congressional affairs for the US Department of Education. The Wolanin Papers document the passage and implementation of the William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program from 1989-1997.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Thomas Wolanin (donor no. 9710 ) and came to the library in March 2006.
The collection is open to research.
From 1975 until 1993, Thomas R. Wolanin worked in various capacities for the US House Committee on Education and Labor, both as staff director and deputy staff director. From 1978 to 1981, 1985-1987 and 1991-1993, he was staff director to the subcommittee on postsecondary education chaired by Congressman William D. Ford. In this later position, Thomas R. Wolanin helped to draft the legislation that would become the William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program, a means by which students would borrow money to pay for their education after high school. Following Ford's retirement, Wolanin moved over to the US Department of Education to serve as deputy assistant secretary for legislation and congressional affairs (1993-1996).
This collection documents Wolanin's work with Representative Ford and the Department of Education on the William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program. The files have been arranged into four series all concerning Federal Direct Lending: Background and Analysis, Legislative Action, Implementation, and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Wolanin, Thomas R., 1942-; Ford, William D.; Student financial aid administration--United States.; Student loans--United States.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Education and Labor.; William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program.
- Direct Lending Background and Analysis
  Background and Analysis (1 linear foot) contains three subseries. Press Coverage is a group of compiled news articles from various periodical publications, including Congressional, economic, educational, mass media, University, and miscellaneous newspapers. This series is arranged alphabetically by type of publication. Political Climate consists of background information regarding the receptiveness towards direct loans by the legislative and executive branches of the government. Student Loans is a collection of reports and position pieces by various student loan stakeholders. This is organized alphabetically by subject addressed.
  - Press Coverage
    - Congressional News (Box 1)
    - Economic News (Box 1)
    - Education News (Box 1)
    - Financial Aid News (Box 1)
    - Mass Media News
      - Associated Press (Box 1)
      - Magazines and Journals (Box 1)
      - Michigan Newspapers (Box 1)
      - New York Newspapers (Box 1)
      - USA Today (Box 1)
      - Washington DC Newspapers (Box 1)
      - Other Newspapers (Box 1)
    - University Newspapers (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Political Climate
    - Executive Branch (Box 1)
    - Legislative Branch (Box 1)
  - Student Loans
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 Audits (Box 1)
    - Alternative Reforms (Box 1)
    - Budget, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Consolidations and Repayment (Box 1)
    - Direct Lending Opposition (Box 1)
    - Direct Lending Program (Box 1)
    - Evaluation of the Federal Direct Loan Program Volume 1 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation of the Federal Direct Loan Program Volume 2, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Guaranteed Student Loans (Box 2)
    - Loan Volume (Box 2)
    - Dissertation: "The Direct Loan Demonstration Program; An Analysis of the Legislative Process Involving Federal Student Loan Policy" by Joe Lew McCormick 1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Direct Lending Legislative Action
  The series Legislative Action (1.2 linear feet) includes documents concerning three major pieces of legislation concerning Direct Loans during Thomas Wolanin's tenure with Representative William D. Ford's staff. The first is the Higher Education Amendments of 1992 (PL 102-325). This then set the stage for the Direct Loan Authorization, a subseries covering all legislative action after the HEA Amendment, leading up to and then directly following the beginning of the direct loan program under the Revenue Reconciliation Act of 1993 (PL 103-66). Leading up to Fiscal Year 1996, the direct loan program came under a great deal of pressure. The sub-series Fiscal Year 1996 Budget Reconciliation includes documentation of legislative action during that time. Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Higher Education Act Amendment of 1992 (Box 2)
  - Direct Loan Authorization of 1993
    - Amendments
      - Unknown Author (Box 2)
      - Robert Andrews (Box 2)
      - Coleman (Box 2)
      - Goodling (Box 2)
      - Burt Gordon (Box 2)
      - Petri (Box 2)
    - Bill Drafts (Box 2)
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - Committee Print (Box 2)
    - Hearings (Box 2)
    - Income-Dependent Education Assistance Act (Box 2)
    - Opposition (Box 2)
      (Led by Burt Gordon)
    - Summary (Box 2)
    - Status Reports (Box 2)
    - Talking Points (Box 2)
  - Fiscal Year 1996 Budget Reconciliation
    - Appropriations Bill (Box 2)
    - Bill Drafts
      - Goodling (Box 2)
      - Istook (Box 2)
      - Kassebaum (Box 2)
      - Petri (Box 2)
      - Simon (Box 2)
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - Conference Bill (Box 2)
    - Credit Reform Scoring (Box 2)
    - Discussion (Box 2)
    - Ford Staff Meetings and Political Intelligence (Box 2)
    - House Actions (Box 2)
    - Information Requests from Congress (Box 2)
    - Opposition (Box 3)
    - Press Conferences (Box 3)
    - Presidential Views (Box 3)
    - Reconciliation Statements (Box 3)
    - Reserves and Guarantee Agencies (Box 3)
    - Senate Actions (Box 3)
- Direct Lending Implementation
  Direct Lending Implementation (0.4 linear feet) is divided into two sub-series, Direct Loan Program and Guaranteed Student Loan Phase-out. And finally, the Correspondence (.4 linear feet) series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or type of correspondent.
  - Direct Loan Program
    - Consolidation Plans (Box 3)
    - Reactions of Schools (Box 3)
    - Republican Concerns (Box 3)
    - Year I-III Participants (Box 3)
  - Guaranteed Student Loan Phase-out
    - Agency Reports (Box 3)
    - Agency Phase-out (Box 3)
- Direct Lending Correspondence
  - Advisory Committee on Student Financial Assistance (Box 3)
  - American Council on Education (Box 3)
  - Congresspeople to Colleagues (Box 3)
  - Department of Education (Box 3)
  - Financial Aid Administrators (Box 3)
  - Financial Institutions (Box 3)
  - General Accounting Office (Box 3)
  - Guarantee Agencies (Box 3)
  - Memoranda (Box 3)
  - Sallie Mae (Box 3)
  - State of Michigan (Box 3)
  - Universities and Colleges (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)